<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent Updates | LISN Lab</title>
    <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lisn-lab.org/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Recent Updates</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lisn-lab.org/media/icon_hu_efe3ed8cd119c4a9.png</url>
      <title>Recent Updates</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>When inner voices become art</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250901-voicesofthemind-workshop1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250901-voicesofthemind-workshop1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The most beautiful experience we can have is the mysterious. It is the source of all true art and science.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ndash; Albert Einstein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The little voice in my head is one such mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have different relationships with the voice in our head. Mine chatters as I read, write, and think. But here&amp;rsquo;s the fascinating part - your inner experience might be completely different from mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While science explains this phenomenon as our brain&amp;rsquo;s silent language production, the reality is far more diverse and intriguing. Some people experience abstract, non-verbal thoughts, others engage in rich inner monologues, and some hear multiple voices in conversation. This remarkable variety of inner experiences has long puzzled psychologists and fascinated artists alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This July, we bridged the gap between science and art by hosting a workshop that invited young people to externalise their thought processes through creative expression. Armed with iPads, paper, keyboards, and microphones, participants transformed their inner worlds into tangible art pieces. We complemented their creative exploration with scientific context, demonstrating EEG recordings of brain activity to show how our thoughts manifest physically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results were extraordinary. Some participants visualised their thoughts as rainbow patterns of emotions, others depicted their inner voice as radio waves, and some translated their mental experience into rhythmic compositions. Each piece offered a unique window into how differently we all experience our inner worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-vimw1&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/a1.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/a1_hu_23bf1c7493b84b.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;a1.png&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;188&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-vimw1&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/a2.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/a2_hu_27191147d5ebcbaf.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;a2.png&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;188&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-vimw1&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/a3.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/a3_hu_31a8426a53fbca1b.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;a3.png&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;188&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-vimw1&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/fightingthought.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/fightingthought_hu_15565aebf0596bc4.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;fightingthought.png&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;175&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-vimw1&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/IMG_3737.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/IMG_3737_hu_11757b4bf6dbd05e.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_3737.jpg&#34; width=&#34;188&#34; height=&#34;250&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-vimw1&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/thebox.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/vimw1/thebox_hu_b52713d79cf2bcdd.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;thebox.png&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;174&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop is part of a larger collaborative project with artists to develop an interactive instrument that allows people to &amp;lsquo;jam out&amp;rsquo; their thoughts and feelings in audiovisual patterns. The prototype will debut at our follow-up workshop on 16th September, and we&amp;rsquo;re excited to see how people will use it to express their own inner experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this matter? Because understanding the diversity of human consciousness isn&amp;rsquo;t just an academic pursuit - it&amp;rsquo;s a gateway to greater empathy and self-awareness. When we realise that everyone&amp;rsquo;s inner experience is unique, we become more accepting of our own mental processes and more understanding of others&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, are you curious about how your inner voice compares to others? Would you like to learn more about language, gender, and design in human-computer interactions? Join us on &lt;strong&gt;16th September 2025 @4-6pm at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gregson.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gregson Centre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, to explore your own mental landscape through our new interactive art installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session will be joined by Dr Bo Yao (Neuroscientist), Charlie Brown (Artist), Steven Hodges (Artist), and Dr Alice Ashcroft (Computer Scientist).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-exclamation-triangle  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Please contact our lead artist Charlie Brown at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:charlie_m_brown@icloud.com&#34;&gt;charlie_m_brown@icloud.com&lt;/a&gt; for more information and to sign up for this event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
More Info:












  












&lt;div class=&#34;card-simple view-card&#34;&gt;

  
    


&lt;div class=&#34;article-metadata&#34;&gt;

  
  

  

  

  

  
  
  
  

  
  

&lt;/div&gt;

  

  
  
  
    
    
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/projects/voicesofthemind/&#34; &gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;img-hover-zoom&#34;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/voicesofthemind_royalsociety_hu_ca2299c553883805.webp&#34; height=&#34;455&#34; width=&#34;808&#34;
            class=&#34;article-banner&#34; alt=&#34;Voices of the Mind&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

  &lt;div class=&#34;section-subheading article-title mb-1 mt-3&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/projects/voicesofthemind/&#34; &gt;Voices of the Mind&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  

  

&lt;/div&gt;



</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calling for Artists to Create Artworks of Inner Speech for Young People</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250409-voicesofthemind-artist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250409-voicesofthemind-artist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-overview--vision&#34;&gt;Project Overview &amp;amp; Vision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/projects/voicesofthemind/&#34;&gt;‘Voices of the Mind’&lt;/a&gt; is a public engagement project that explores inner speech - the internal dialogue we have with our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to empower young people aged 14-18 from diverse backgrounds with knowledge about their inner experiences, create interdisciplinary dialogue between science and art, reduce stigma around different thought patterns, and make neuroscience accessible to those traditionally underrepresented in STEM fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking artists to create engaging works that interpret and visualise inner speech / thoughts, helping young people understand, relate to, and reflect upon their inner speech while sparking curiosity about neuroscience and AI. Your work will feature in public exhibitions, workshops, and online platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;commission-details&#34;&gt;Commission Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Budget Available&lt;/strong&gt;: £4,500 (can be allocated to one artist or be divided among multiple artists)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timeline&lt;/strong&gt;: Commissions to be completed by end of September 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theme&lt;/strong&gt;: Inner speech, inner thoughts, and the experience of hearing voices within our minds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/u&gt;: We particularly welcome proposals that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make abstract thought processes tangible and relatable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Represent the diversity of inner speech / thought experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create opportunities for reflection on how we think and talk to ourselves in the mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore the boundaries between typical inner speech and more intrusive thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Format&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/u&gt;: We prioritise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital&lt;/strong&gt; art that can be shared online and incorporated into our digital platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portable&lt;/strong&gt; physical installations that can travel between multiple events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive&lt;/strong&gt; elements that engage audiences and encourage participation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example Project Ideas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/u&gt;: We welcome innovative approaches beyond these suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Animated Short Film&lt;/u&gt;: A visual journey through inner thoughts, perhaps showing how they flow, interact, or evolve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Interactive VR Environment&lt;/u&gt;: An immersive virtual space where users experience different forms of inner speech as they navigate (could be a VR app or a 2D POV film illustrating spontaneous thought patterns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;Audio Installation&lt;/u&gt;: A layered soundscape using multiple voices to represent the variety and complexity of inner speech (we can provide recordings of real self-talk as source material)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;submission-requirements&#34;&gt;Submission Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Artist statement explaining your motivation and interest in this project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A concept description&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual/auditory references, sketches or examples of the proposed work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical requirements, production plan, and timeline for completion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Budget breakdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;selection-criteria&#34;&gt;Selection Criteria&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposals will be evaluated on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Artistic quality and innovation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feasibility within budget and timeline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alignment with project aims and audience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intractability, portability and adaptability for various settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact-and-submission&#34;&gt;Contact and Submission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please submit your proposal to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:b.yao1@lancaster.ac.uk&#34;&gt;b.yao1@lancaster.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;30th May 2025&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We particularly encourage applications from artists from diverse backgrounds and those with connections to Northwest England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
More Info:












  












&lt;div class=&#34;card-simple view-card&#34;&gt;

  
    


&lt;div class=&#34;article-metadata&#34;&gt;

  
  

  

  

  

  
  
  
  

  
  

&lt;/div&gt;

  

  
  
  
    
    
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/projects/voicesofthemind/&#34; &gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;img-hover-zoom&#34;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/voicesofthemind_royalsociety_hu_ca2299c553883805.webp&#34; height=&#34;455&#34; width=&#34;808&#34;
            class=&#34;article-banner&#34; alt=&#34;Voices of the Mind&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

  &lt;div class=&#34;section-subheading article-title mb-1 mt-3&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/projects/voicesofthemind/&#34; &gt;Voices of the Mind&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  

  

&lt;/div&gt;



</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LISN Lab Celebrates a Memorable EPS Lancaster Experience</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250407-epslancaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250407-epslancaster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What a vibrant few days we had at the Experimental Psychology Society conference in Lancaster! The LISN Lab team returned to the lab energised, inspired, and with notebooks full of new ideas after engaging with the psychological research community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference halls buzzed with excitement as our researchers shared their latest discoveries. We dived deep into the fascinating world of how languages, which place different emphases on the subject or the overall topic, are underpinned by different structural representations in the brain. Meanwhile, conversations flourished around our presentations on how our life experiences shape abstract thinking - it turns out those episodic memories don&amp;rsquo;t just help us remember the past, they fundamentally influence how we mentally construct concepts like &amp;ldquo;freedom&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;justice&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve really enjoyed the discussions about our work on inner speech. When that little voice in your head speaks, how do the motor and auditory speech mechanisms work together, differently and dynamically? Our findings on how perceptual reactivation plays a key role in shaping inner speech experiences into different forms prompted many attendees to reflect on their own inner speech experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-2025eps&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/guyutalk.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/guyutalk_hu_c9cc25426814203b.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;guyutalk.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;188&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-2025eps&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/jiaxuantalk.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/jiaxuantalk_hu_4a76a9246dd84a8f.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;jiaxuantalk.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;203&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-2025eps&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/poster_guyujiaxuan.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/poster_guyujiaxuan_hu_5022cb7283dfd511.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;poster_guyujiaxuan.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;188&#34; height=&#34;250&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-2025eps&#34; href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/poster.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/media/albums/2025eps/poster_hu_fd370e65bf96f9c8.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;poster.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;188&#34; height=&#34;250&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire event flowed seamlessly thanks to the tremendous efforts of Padraic, Alice, and all the local organisers who transformed academic presentations into a genuine community experience. Their thoughtful planning created spaces not just for formal knowledge exchange, but for the kind of spontaneous interactions that often spark the most innovative ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we settle back into our research routines, we carry with us new connections, fresh insights, and renewed enthusiasm for our research questions. Stay tuned as we build on these experiences in our upcoming work!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inner speechless: Is it possible to have no inner speech?</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250131-anendophasia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250131-anendophasia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Close your eyes for a moment and listen. What do you hear? For most of us, beyond any external sounds, there&amp;rsquo;s that familiar voice inside our head - our inner speech.  But have you ever wondered, what if that voice weren’t there at all? Is it possible to have no inner speech?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us can’t imagine going about our daily lives without ‘the voice inside our head’;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inner voice mediates many of the mechanisms that allow us to perceive the world around us, such as reading and memory. It also encourages us when we need it, keeps our focus when our minds drift and helps us problem-solve and reason. Sometimes, it can even be exploited by our doubts and anxieties to talk us down. The 20th-century, Russian psychologist Lev Vygotsky, in his theory of cognitive development, proposed that we are born social beings. Over time, the conversations we have with those in our surroundings eventually become &lt;em&gt;‘internalised’&lt;/em&gt;, and we discuss our behaviour with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through conversations with my peers, I learned just how varied this cognitive tool can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Wm33v9spP9Q?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that some individuals described their inner speech as largely grammatical, resembling full, structured sentences. Others reported that their inner voices focus exclusively on the semantic meaning, rather than the grammatical features. This type of inner speech is akin to jotting down brief notes that capture only the essential points, also known as &lt;em&gt;condensed inner speech&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people said they use their inner voices to evaluate their own behavior and actions—to criticize or encourage themselves, with varying degrees of each, and one individual even said their mind is focused on this ‘24/7’. This &lt;em&gt;‘evaluative inner speech’&lt;/em&gt; has been shown to affect our mental states and moods, with some people noting that it helps them feel calmer, while others said it makes them feel more anxious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complexity of inner speech becomes even more apparent when we consider multilingual individuals. When discussing this topic with a bilingual friend, she shared that, although Hebrew was her first language and the primary language spoken at home, her inner speech has consistently been in English for as long as she can remember. She explained, ‘Even though I didn’t learn it first, it’s the language I’ve grown up around, went to school speaking and it&amp;rsquo;s the language I’m most comfortable using.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fascination doesn’t stop there. There’s also a difference in how people experience their inner voices: some say it feels like they’re speaking to themselves, while others feel more like they’re listening to somebody else. Some also report more vivid inner speech when reading, a context in which many describe inner speech that varies in tone, pitch or even accent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidently, there are a diverse range of uses and forms of inner voice experience. Varying in terms of our perspectives and environments and producing further differences in our moods and mental states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises an intriguing question: Is it possible for someone to have no inner speech at all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Anendophasia&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/20250131-anendophasia/anendophasia2_hu_69235bdee1a5b10a.webp 400w,
               /post/20250131-anendophasia/anendophasia2_hu_f0f0ffa295334bd5.webp 760w,
               /post/20250131-anendophasia/anendophasia2_hu_cee99471ba334f33.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250131-anendophasia/anendophasia2_hu_69235bdee1a5b10a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;600&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This area is receiving growing attention, and the answer appears to be yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of us, there is still a line between our inner version of speech, and what researchers call ‘unsymbolised’ concepts – abstract thoughts that aren’t expressed in words. While some report calling upon images instead of words when thinking, others describe experiencing only these unsymbolized thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when reading, some people who lack inner speech describe comprehension of sentences in ‘concepts’, purely abstract and remote from the written text in front of them. They report understanding meaning directly, without consciously processing the words themselves.  Some even describe struggling to think of sentences without saying them verbally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of individuals who lack inner speech has been documented not only with subjective reports but also with objective, behavioural tasks. Researchers coined the term ‘anendophasia’ to describe a lack of inner speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent study, Nedergaard &amp;amp; Lupyan (2024) examined the differences in cognition between those with inner speech and anendophasics. They gave both groups tasks that typically rely upon inner speech and compared their performance. Their findings were intriguing, recall for verbal working memory, which is closely related to inner speech, was higher for those with inner speech than those without.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that many individuals consistently report not using, or even not having, inner speech, we can conclude with confidence that the phenomenon of anendophasia is, in fact, a real experience for some people. When results appear to be the same in populations with and without inner speech, this may be because anendophasics have developed alternative cognitive mechanisms to handle behavioral tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fascinating dimension of human inner experience creates further interesting questions about the possible consequences of anendophasia on cognition, attention, perception, and mental wellbeing. The implications are far-reaching – from how we approach teaching children who might process words differently, to how we conduct talking therapy when some individuals might not experience thoughts in verbal form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about you? Do you have inner speech? What is it like for you?  We&amp;rsquo;re particularly interested in hearing from people who don&amp;rsquo;t experience inner speech or who think differently without using words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, we&amp;rsquo;re currently conducting an exciting study using EEG to understand how different people process memories, especially those who might not use inner speech. If you&amp;rsquo;d like to contribute to our understanding of this fascinating phenomenon, we&amp;rsquo;d love to hear from you and potentially have you participate in our research.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.office.com/Pages/ResponsePage.aspx?id=Ec2bnHqXnE6poLxzQJAWSkfutwuiw5VOt6BaX9Yki5pUNVI2QlFaNUlVVVpSU0ExMUhUN0hVODNWWS4u&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have an inner speech! Sign Me Up!&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lack of mental imagery? You may be special!</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250121-aphantasia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20250121-aphantasia/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-aphantasia&#34;&gt;What is Aphantasia?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#does-aphantasia-affect-everyday-life&#34;&gt;Does Aphantasia Affect Everyday Life?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-surprising-benefits-of-aphantasia&#34;&gt;The Surprising Benefits of Aphantasia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-about-you&#34;&gt;What About You?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#contributing-to-research&#34;&gt;Contributing to Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of an apple in your mind. Can you see a red fruit with a glossy sheen, or… nothing at all? If it is the latter, then &lt;strong&gt;you may be part of 2-4% of the world’s population that are aphantasic!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry - aphantasia isn&amp;rsquo;t a disability or medical condition. It&amp;rsquo;s simply a different way that the mind processes information and thinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-aphantasia&#34;&gt;What is Aphantasia?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aphantasia is when your brain doesn’t form or use mental images as part of your thinking or imagination. If your mind is like a TV, for someone with Aphantasia, it is as if the screen is blank, with no shapes or colours or… anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This affects even the most familiar objects. For instance, someone I interviewed said they can’t even imagine objects they use every day, such as their phone. They can think about their phone as a concept but literally cannot picture it in their head!
Aphantasia can be congenital (from birth) or acquired (developed in later life, often due to illness / injury / mental health condition) and doesn’t need diagnosing. In fact, people often don’t even realise that they are aphantasic, even though they may notice from a young age they lack the ability to form mental images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in a BBC news article Niel Kenmuir said that as a child, he couldn’t fall asleep counting sheep – not because he didn’t want to, but because he simply couldn’t see the sheep in his mind! He didn’t realise this was unusual until adulthood. Indeed, many people didn’t realise until later in life that they were aphantasic, but did notice from a young age that they could not picture things in their mind like others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;does-aphantasia-affect-everyday-life&#34;&gt;Does Aphantasia Affect Everyday Life?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aphantasia rarely affects everyday life, as it doesn’t stop them from doing things.
However, Aphantasia does impact certain abilities, such as not being able to picture what book characters look like when reading, or finding arts and geometry hard because they can’t manipulate images or shapes in their mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Aphantasics experience very poor visual memory – it’d be a struggle for them to recall images from significant events like wedding or their first day at school, and sometimes even to recognise faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-surprising-benefits-of-aphantasia&#34;&gt;The Surprising Benefits of Aphantasia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While having Aphantasia isn’t a limitation – it’s just a different way of thinking. Research suggests it may actually enhance certain cognitive abilities. People with aphantasia often excel in analytical thinking and abstract reasoning, demonstrating superior factual memory and logical problem-solving skills. Additionally, some aphantasic individuals report practical advantages, such as being less affected by traumatic visual memories or disturbing descriptions in books or movies, as they process information conceptually rather than visually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-you&#34;&gt;What About You?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you curious about how your own mind works? Can you picture an apple? Do you have mental imagery? Have you ever wondered if you might be aphantasic? Understanding your cognitive style can provide valuable insights into how you learn, process information, and interact with the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contributing-to-research&#34;&gt;Contributing to Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your experience matters to the scientific community. As part of our ongoing research into neurodiversity, we&amp;rsquo;re conducting a study on how aphantasia affects cognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think you are Aphantasic and would like to contribute to our understanding of this fascinating variation in human cognition, please join our research by signing up through the link below.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.office.com/Pages/ResponsePage.aspx?id=Ec2bnHqXnE6poLxzQJAWSrFgdYO91ptHjgdJqGlvLhxUNUQ4RDZONVdCNjlGVUJHSU1HVVZXT1E5OC4u&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Yay! Sign Me Up!&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STARS Squad Kicks Off Journal Club with a Bang!</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20241030-stars-journalclub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20241030-stars-journalclub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our new STARS squad launched their first journal club this week, and it was a hit! Maisie led an engaging discussion on the Variety of Inner Speech Questionnaire-Revised, sparking interesting conversations about inner speech, cultural norms, and individual experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explored how questionnaires like the VISQ can be improved and validated, and potentially be adapted for clinical contexts. We also dipped our toes into the fascinating world of schizophrenia and predictive brain models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t all work, though - Summer&amp;rsquo;s Halloween-themed biscuits added a festive touch to the proceedings. The enthusiasm in the room was palpable, with every member eager to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This successful start sets the stage for an exciting term ahead. Each STAR will have the chance to shine, engaging with a diverse range of topics and lively debates. Stay tuned for more updates!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exciting Funding News!</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20241001-apex-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/post/20241001-apex-award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our lab has been awarded &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsociety.org/news/2024/09/apex-awards/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;an APEX Award by the Royal Society&lt;/a&gt; for an exciting project towards EEG Classification of Auditory Verbal Hallucinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research aims to advance the understanding and detection of internal speech experiences akin to auditory verbal hallucinations (AVHs) by combining electroencephalography (EEG) with explainable machine learning. This cross-disciplinary approach brings together experts from neuroscience, psychology, and computer science to develop a potentially game-changing method for monitoring and treating AVHs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited about the possibilities this project opens up and the potential to improve the lives of those affected by AVHs. Stay tuned for updates as we embark on this exciting new chapter in our research!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
