<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Structural Processing | LISN Lab</title>
    <link>https://lisn-lab.org/tag/structural-processing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lisn-lab.org/tag/structural-processing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Structural Processing</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lisn-lab.org/media/icon_hu_efe3ed8cd119c4a9.png</url>
      <title>Structural Processing</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/tag/structural-processing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Language</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/research/language/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/research/language/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#abstract-concepts&#34;&gt;Abstract Concepts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#structural-processing&#34;&gt;Structural Processing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#eye-movements-in-reading&#34;&gt;Eye Movements in Reading&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#language-and-emotion&#34;&gt;Language and Emotion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At LISN, we investigate language processing through multiple complementary lenses, from fundamental cognitive mechanisms to complex emotional interactions. Our research spans four key areas: the representation of abstract concepts, structural processing within and across languages, eye movements during reading, and the interaction between language and emotion. Through this multi-faceted approach, we aim to develop a comprehensive understanding of how humans process, comprehend, and experience language. Our work combines diverse methodologies - from precise eye-tracking measurements to cognitive-behavioral studies - enabling us to examine language processing at various levels of analysis.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract-concepts&#34;&gt;Abstract Concepts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract concepts like &amp;ldquo;love&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;trust&amp;rdquo; pose a unique challenge in cognitive science. Unlike concrete concepts such as &amp;ldquo;red,&amp;rdquo; which derive meaning from direct sensory experiences, abstract concepts lack physical referents. This absence raises questions about how such concepts are represented in the mind and complicates the prevailing &amp;rsquo;embodied&amp;rsquo; theory of concept representation, which suggests that concepts gain meaning through bodily experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LISN, we tackle these challenges by exploring alternative grounding for abstract concepts. We investigate whether emotional or metaphorical experiences provide the basis for understanding abstract words. For example, &amp;rsquo;trust&amp;rsquo; is often considered a &amp;lsquo;big&amp;rsquo; concept because it elicits strong emotions &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2013-YVWSOS-PlosONE&#34;&gt;(Yao et al., 2013)&lt;/a&gt; and is metaphorically associated with large objects like &amp;lsquo;castle&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;cathedral&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2022-YTS-JML&#34;&gt;(Yao, Taylor, &amp;amp; Sereno, 2022)&lt;/a&gt;. Our research also examines the possibility that abstract concepts have a more episodic and context-dependent grounding compared to concrete ones. For instance, the concept of &amp;rsquo;love&amp;rsquo; can vary significantly depending on the context, such as a romantic dinner or a care home, unlike more concrete concepts like &amp;lsquo;cat,&amp;rsquo; which consistently evoke features like fur and paws. We extend this inquiry to understand how embodied experiences influence language comprehension across various contexts and life stages.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;structural-processing&#34;&gt;Structural Processing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural processing in language is a complex cognitive function that extends beyond mere syntax. It involves breaking down sentences into components such as subjects, verbs, and objects, and understanding their interrelationships to extract meaning. This function also intersects with other cognitive domains like prosody - the intonation in spoken sentences - and arithmetic operations, highlighting its role as a domain-general mechanism crucial for structuring language, cognition, and communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LISN, our focus is twofold. First, we explore the link between implicit prosody in reading, commonly known as &amp;ldquo;inner speech,&amp;rdquo; and syntactic processing. This helps us understand how the &amp;lsquo;melody&amp;rsquo; of language in our minds influences sentence interpretation &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2018-YS-Cognition&#34;&gt;(Yao &amp;amp; Scheepers, 2018)&lt;/a&gt;. Second, we study how sentence structures in different languages affect cognition among their speakers. For example, Chinese sentences often omit subjects and focus on topics, whereas English sentences require subjects and emphasise them. This difference could lead to varying attentional focuses and mental representations. We also examine the contrasting structures between left-branching languages like Chinese and right-branching languages like English, suggesting different structural hierarchies between languages. Through these investigations, we aim to untangle the complexities of structural processing and its influence on cognition and communication.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;eye-movements-in-reading&#34;&gt;Eye Movements in Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eye movements in reading offer a rich data source for understanding cognitive processes such as attention, memory, and language comprehension. Captured through eye-tracking technology, these movements include quick jumps called saccades and brief pauses known as fixations, where most information absorption takes place. Factors like text complexity and reader familiarity affect the duration of these fixations and the length of saccades. The parafoveal region of the eye also provides a &amp;lsquo;preview&amp;rsquo; of upcoming words during saccades, facilitating smoother reading. Lexical variables such as word frequency, predictability, and orthography further influence these eye movements, offering insights into ocular control and cognitive processes in reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LISN, we engage in targeted research projects to explore this complex landscape. For instance, one study examines the interaction between word frequency and contextual predictability in relation to parafoveal preview, aiming to understand their combined impact on fixation durations &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2018-SWLYH-QJEP&#34;&gt;(Sereno et al., 2018)&lt;/a&gt;. Another research line investigates how altering the perceptual quality of the parafoveal preview might affect the processing of the previewed word&amp;rsquo;s spelling, subsequently influencing lexical selection in later fixations. Through these studies, LISN aims to clarify the multifaceted factors that influence eye movements in reading, thereby enriching broader theories of cognition and language processing.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;language-and-emotion&#34;&gt;Language and Emotion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processing of emotion words involves a complex interplay between language and emotional cognition. One layer of complexity arises from the interaction between a word&amp;rsquo;s concreteness and its emotional valence. For example, concrete emotion words like &amp;ldquo;kiss&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;snake&amp;rdquo; often elicit stronger emotional and cognitive responses than abstract ones like &amp;ldquo;love&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;fear,&amp;rdquo; likely because they more easily evoke sensory experiences. Beyond this, the processing of emotion words is influenced by various factors such as the individual&amp;rsquo;s current emotional state, cultural background, and the context in which the word appears. For instance, a positive mood may facilitate the processing of positively-valenced words, while a negative mood could have the opposite effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LISN, we focus on these nuanced interactions. We examine how concreteness and emotional valence in word processing interact, particularly in the context of alexithymia—a condition characterised by difficulties in identifying and describing emotions &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2018-YKBSOS-JEPLMC&#34;&gt;(Yao et al., 2018)&lt;/a&gt;. We also investigate how emotional experiences provide an embodied basis for understanding abstract concepts, thereby extending the &amp;rsquo;embodied cognition&amp;rsquo; framework to include emotional and abstract language. For example, the abstract concept of &amp;ldquo;freedom&amp;rdquo; may be more deeply understood through the emotional experience of relief or exhilaration &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2013-YVWSOS-PlosONE&#34;&gt;(Yao et al., 2013)&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, we explore the role of mood states in emotion word processing, investigating how they can alter the perceived emotional charge of words &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2015-SSYTO-FrontierPsych&#34;&gt;(Sereno et al., 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. Through these research avenues, LISN aims to offer a comprehensive understanding of emotion word processing, enriching both theoretical frameworks and practical applications in cognitive science.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voice Hearing</title>
      <link>https://lisn-lab.org/research/voicehearing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lisn-lab.org/research/voicehearing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#voice-hearing-continuum&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing Continuum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#voice-hearing-as-predictions&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing as Predictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#voice-hearing-transition-risks&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing Transition Risks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#voice-hearing-interventions&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing Interventions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voice hearing research spans multiple interconnected domains, from understanding its prevalence in the general population to developing innovative interventions. At LISN, we take a comprehensive approach to studying this complex phenomenon. Our research examines voice hearing across four key areas: its existence as a continuous spectrum in the population, the critical factors influencing transition to clinical conditions, the underlying predictive mechanisms in the brain, and the development of novel therapeutic interventions. By investigating these interrelated aspects, we aim to advance both theoretical understanding and practical treatments for voice hearing experiences.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;voice-hearing-continuum&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing Continuum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voice hearing exists on a spectrum and is not limited to clinical populations. It involves a range of experiences, from hearing one&amp;rsquo;s name to complex dialogues, and can be distressing or benign. This natural variation in human experience has been studied through neuroscientific and psychological approaches, exploring its neural and cognitive correlates, while cultural factors also play a role. Understanding this spectrum has implications for mental health treatment, challenging associated stigma and informing therapeutic interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LISN, our research focuses on cognitive abilities and biases predictive of voice hearing tendencies across this spectrum. We particularly examine signal detection theory (SDT) performance, where both nonclinical and clinical voice hearers often exhibit an externalising bias, perceiving internal voices as originating externally. Through rigorous experimental methods, we compare SDT performance among individuals to understand how this bias may be influenced by auditory verbal hallucination (AVH) proneness, variations in corollary discharge, memory inhibition, and other individual factors. Through this focus, LISN aims to offer a nuanced understanding of the cognitive mechanisms underlying the voice hearing spectrum.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;voice-hearing-as-predictions&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing as Predictions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voice hearing has been increasingly studied within the predictive coding framework, which describes perception as a process of hypothesis testing. In this framework, auditory verbal hallucinations (AVH) may arise from an imbalance between top-down predictions and bottom-up sensory input. This fundamental brain mechanism has been explored through various factors, such as neurotransmitter systems, cognitive biases, and socio-emotional factors. This perspective offers a generalised understanding of voice hearing and opens new avenues for prognosis, diagnosis and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LISN, we focus on experimentally manipulating predictions and sensory input to understand voice hearing better. Methods include conditioning, articulatory suppression, earworm induction, and exposure to different types of auditory noises. We assess the impacts of these manipulations on signal detection task (SDT) performance and self-reported voice hearing experiences &lt;a href=&#34;https://lisn-lab.org/publication/2023-MCPKY-FiN&#34;&gt;(Mak et al., 2023)&lt;/a&gt;. By demonstrating how voice hearing arises from natural brain processes, we aim to develop methods to characterise voice hearing tendencies across the population. This research helps us understand its prevalence and transition risks to psychosis, while contributing to broader efforts to normalize these experiences and reduce stigma, particularly in underserved communities.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;voice-hearing-transition-risks&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing Transition Risks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transition from voice hearing to psychosis is a critical but relatively uncommon area of study in mental health research. While many people experience voice hearing without transitioning to clinical states like psychosis, understanding the factors that contribute to this transition is crucial for early intervention. Research has identified risk factors such as frequency and distress level of voice hearing, comorbid symptoms, and environmental stressors. Neurobiological markers and the concept of a &amp;ldquo;clinical high-risk state&amp;rdquo; have also been studied to identify those at increased risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with the Greater Manchester Mental Health NHS Foundation Trust, LISN conducts pioneering research to understand the transition risks among nonclinical voice hearers. Our research focuses on understanding these risks as neurodevelopmental vulnerabilities, which manifest through increasingly complex voice hearing experiences. We also aim to understand the underlying cognitive and neural mechanisms that contribute to this transition. Through this targeted research, LISN seeks to offer insights into the factors that may lead to the transition from voice hearing to psychosis, with the goal of informing early intervention and prevention strategies.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;voice-hearing-interventions&#34;&gt;Voice Hearing Interventions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interventions for voice hearing have evolved to include a range of approaches, from pharmacological treatments to psychological therapies like CBT and mindfulness. Advanced techniques like neurostimulation and neurofeedback offer targeted, brain-based interventions. Neurostimulation methods like TMS and tDCS modulate neural activity, while neurofeedback teaches self-regulation through real-time brain monitoring. These methods are less reliant on medication and offer the promise of more personalised treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LISN, our focus is on developing an EEG-tDCS closed-loop type of online intervention for voice hearing. This innovative system uses EEG to identify voice hearing states in real-time, while tDCS provides targeted intervention to prevent escalation into psychotic episodes. While this cutting-edge approach is still under development, it represents the ultimate goal of our lab in studying voice hearing. Through this pioneering technology, LISN aims to offer a more immediate and targeted intervention, potentially revolutionising the treatment landscape for voice hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
