<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Voice of the Mind Project | LISN Lab</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/voice-of-the-mind-project/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/voice-of-the-mind-project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Voice of the Mind Project</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu_efe3ed8cd119c4a9.png</url>
      <title>Voice of the Mind Project</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/voice-of-the-mind-project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Artists to Create Works That Interpret and Illustrate Inner Speech to Empower Young People</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/20250409-voicesofthemind-artist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/20250409-voicesofthemind-artist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-overview--vision&#34;&gt;Project Overview &amp;amp; Vision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Voices of the Mind’ is a public engagement project that explores inner speech - the internal dialogue we have with our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to empower young people from diverse backgrounds with knowledge about their inner experiences, create interdisciplinary dialogue between science and art, reduce stigma around different thought patterns, and make neuroscience accessible to those traditionally underrepresented in STEM fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking artists to create engaging works that interpret and visualise inner speech / thoughts, helping young people understand, relate to, and reflect upon their inner speech while sparking curiosity about neuroscience and AI. Your work will feature in public exhibitions, workshops, and online platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;commission-details&#34;&gt;Commission Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Total Budget Available&lt;/em&gt;: £4,500 (can be allocated to one artist or divided among multiple artists)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timeline: Commissions to be completed by September 2025
• Theme: Inner speech, inner thoughts, and the experience of hearing voices within our minds
Focus: We particularly welcome proposals that:
• Make abstract thought processes tangible and relatable
• Represent the diversity of inner speech / thought experiences
• Create opportunities for reflection on how we think and talk to ourselves in the mind
• Explore the boundaries between typical inner speech and more intrusive thoughts
Format: We prioritise:
• Digital art that can be shared online and incorporated into our digital platforms
• Portable physical installations that can travel between multiple events
• Interactive elements that engage audiences and encourage participation
Example Project Ideas: We welcome innovative approaches beyond these suggestions:
• Animated Short Film: A visual journey through inner thoughts, perhaps showing how they flow, interact, or evolve
• Interactive VR Environment: An immersive virtual space where users experience different forms of inner speech as they navigate (could be a VR app or a 2D POV film illustrating spontaneous thought patterns)
• Audio Installation: A layered soundscape using multiple voices to represent the variety and complexity of inner speech (we can provide recordings of real self-talk as source material)
Submission Requirements
Please provide:
• Artist statement explaining your motivation and interest in this project
• A concept description
• Visual/auditory references, sketches or examples of the proposed work
• Technical requirements, production plan, and timeline for completion
• Budget breakdown
Selection Criteria
Proposals will be evaluated on:
• Artistic quality and innovation
• Feasibility within budget and timeline
• Alignment with project aims and audience
• Intractability, portability and adaptability for various settings
Contact and Submission
Please submit your proposal to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:b.yao1@lancaster.ac.uk&#34;&gt;b.yao1@lancaster.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt; by 30th May 2025.
For questions or further information, contact Dr Bo Yao at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:b.yao1@lancaster.ac.uk&#34;&gt;b.yao1@lancaster.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;.
We particularly encourage applications from artists from diverse backgrounds and those with connections to Northwest England.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
